Papers of George C. Baker 1903-1958 (bulk 1943-1957)
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections
- Correspondence, 1931, 1940-1958; Series II
  - Letter from John B. Carroll, American Council of Learned Studies (ACLS), to Barker, March 24, 1954; Expresses approval of Barker’s research proposal for an interdisciplinary study of Mexican bilingualism in Los Angeles, and informs him that the ACLS Committee on the Language Program will help procure funds. (Box 2, Folder 4, Item 3)
  - Letter from Einar Haugen, Univ. of Wisc., to Prof. John B. Carroll, March 31, 1954; Supports and endorses Barker’s proposal to Carroll for the study. (Box 2, Folder 4, Item 4)
  - Letter from John B. Carroll, ACLS, to Barker, April 20, 1954; Reports on the comments received from Einar Haugen and Mary Haas. (Box 2, Folder 4, Item 5)
  - Letter from John B. Carroll, ACLS, to Barker, May 19, 1954; Informs Barker that he may delay the submission of his revised proposal. (Box 2, Folder 4, Item 6)
  - Postcard from Pacific Palisades Art Association to Mr. and Mrs. Barker, [Sr.?], September 3, 1954; Announcement of a lecture to be given by Barker followed by a lecture on Spanish art given by George, Sr. (Box 2, Folder 4, Item 7)
  - Letter from Barker to John B. Carroll, ACLS, September 15, 1954; Informs Carroll he will send the revised proposal by the end of the month. (Box 2, Folder 4, Item 8)
  - Letter from John B. Carroll, ACLS, to Barker, October 7, 1954; Carroll received the proposal, and gives Barker the addresses of other members of the Committee on the Language Program. (Box 2, Folder 4, Item 9)
  - Letter from Jose Perez Vidal to Barker, October 29, 1954; Transmits Cantos populares españoles, Seville, 1882, and envelope (in Spanish). (Box 2, Folder 4, Item 10)
  - Letter from Albert H. Marckwardt to Barker, November 19, 1954; Asks for a copy of Barker’s research proposal submitted to the ACLS. (Box 2, Folder 4, Item 11)
  - Letter from Leslie E. Eichelberger to Barker, March 18, 1955; Discusses Barker's Neighborhood Association work. (Box 2, Folder 4, Item 12)
  - Letter from Joseph B. Casagrande to Barker, April 11, 1955; Accompanies report on a “work conference on bilingualism” and two papers. (Box 2, Folder 4, Item 13)
  - Letter from Sister Celine, S.S.S., to Barker, April 19, 1955; Promises support for Barker's "cultural influence'' study of a Catholic Youth Organization club in Los Angeles, Calif. (Box 2, Folder 4, Item 14)
  - Letter from Barker to Ed [i.e. Edward Dozier], July 29, 1955; Comments on the Southwestern Project In Comparative Psycholinguistics and on his own bilingual study entitled at that point, "A Study of Communication Patterns and Social Isolation among Mexican American Boys' Gangs in Los Angeles.” (Box 2, Folder 4, Item 15)
  - Letter from Ed [i.e. Edward Dozier] to Barker, August 12, 1955; Contains information on goals and working techniques of the Southwestern Project in Comparative Psycholinguistics. (Box 2, Folder 4, Item 16)
  - Letter from William Whitley to Barker, August 23, 1955; Acknowledges interest Barker was taking in a special series of CBS Television Pacific Network. (Box 2, Folder 4, Item 17)
  - Letter from Barker to Mr. A.F. Schaeffer, September 15, 1955; Concerns U.S. Public Health Service research grant application administrative matters. (Box 2, Folder 4, Item 18)
  - Letter from Barker to Harold R. Muntz, October 4, 1955; Transmits the results of his language study to the Los Angeles County Probation Department. (Box 2, Folder 4, Item 19)
  - Postcard from Bill Gutierrez to Barker, October 9, 1955; Asks for a copy of the boys' gang study in Los Angeles. (Box 2, Folder 4, Item 20)
  - Letter from Mrs. W.L. Clemens to Barker, December 5, 1955; Thanks Barker for participating in a panel [at Puente High School?]. (Box 2, Folder 4, Item 21)
  - Letter from Barker to Dr. Corbato, December 15, 1955; Transmits paper on penitential processions in Spain. Corbato returns the letter with annotations. (Box 2, Folder 4, Item 22)
  - Letter from Edmund O. Barker to Barker, March 24, 1956; Contains bibliographical material on the Mexican shepherds' play and mentions the "‘boycott trials’ of the Negroes in Montgomery.” (Box 2, Folder 4, Item 23)
  - Letter from Father Radtke [et al.] to "Dear Parishioner,", March, 1956; Announces the Easter ceremonies of the Sacred Heart Church in Nogales, Ariz. (Box 2, Folder 4, Item 24)
  - Letter from Barker to Ed [i.e. Edward Dozier], June 13, 1956; Announces a field trip to New Mexico to observe the San Buenaventura celebrations at Cochiti for his study of "Catholic ritual processions in Spain and the American Southwest" and also expresses the hope to be able to talk to members of the psycholinguistic project. (Box 2, Folder 4, Item 25)
  - Anonymous postcard to Barker, August 28, 1956; Postcard consists of a hand-drawn map. (Box 2, Folder 4, Item 26)
  - Letter from Frances Gillmor to Barker, October 15, 1956; Thanks Barker for participating in a panel on folk drama at the folklore meeting. (Box 2, Folder 4, Item 27)
  - Letter from Barker to Mr. Herrera, November l, 1956; Asks the Governor of Cochiti Pueblo questions about the corn dance and procession of the feast day of San Buenaventura. (Box 2, Folder 4, Item 28)
  - Letter from Barker to Ed [i.e. Edward Dozier], December 13, 1956; Comments on "Ed's" [i.e. Dozier’s?] paper on evaluating "aboriginal rituals from the standpoints of degree of sacredness, extend of community participation, and extent of public visibility and outside participation." (Box 2, Folder 4, Item 29)
  - Letter from Ed [i.e. Edward Dozier] to Barker, December 16, 1956; Contains further information about Pueblo Catholicism and Indian ceremonies in reply to Barker's letter (cf. above letter). (Box 2, Folder 4, Item 30)
  - Letter from Barker to Edward P. Dozier, January 4, 1957; Acknowledges help given by Dozier at the meeting in Santa Monica and refers to their papers on Pueblo materials. (Box 2, Folder 5, Item 1)
  - Letter from Ed [i.e. Edward Dozier] to Barker, January 14, 1957; Talks about the possibility of publishing the three papers on Pueblo and Yaqui materials together (Edward Spicer, Edward Dozier, and Barker). (Box 2, Folder 5, Item 2)
  - Letter from Frances Gillmor to Barker, January 16, 1957; Thanks Barker for the wonderful Santa Monica meetings. (Box 2, Folder 5, Item 3)
  - Letter from Wayland D. Hand to Barker, January 18, 1957; Friendly note. (Box 2, Folder 5, Item 4)
  - Letter from Barker to Ned [i.e. Edward Spicer], January 19, 1957; Discusses the joint publishing venture for the three papers again. (Box 2, Folder 5, Item 5)
  - Letter from Thomas A. Sebeok to Barker, January 31, 1957; Friendly note referring to recent meetings. (Box 2, Folder 5, Item 6)
  - Letter from Edward H. Spicer to Barker, February 1, 1957; Agrees to the joint publishing of the three papers on Pueblo and Yaqui materials. Agrees to do the overall comments. (Box 2, Folder 5, Item 7)
  - Letter from Barker to Ned [i.e. Edward Spicer], February 7, 1957; Comments on the three papers in regard to Linton's Acculturation in Seven American Indian Tribes. (Box 2, Folder 5, Item 8)
  - Letter from Ed [i.e. Edward Dozier] to Barker, March 20, 1957; Comments on his [Dozier’s] intended revisions to his paper planned for publication with Barker’s and Spicer’s. (Box 2, Folder 5, Item 9)
  - Letter from Sheilagh Brooks and Richard H. Brooks to Barker, April 27, 1957; Mentions their fieldwork in northwestern Mexico and also refers to a Los pastores manuscript they have collected. (Box 2, Folder 5, Item 10)
  - Letter from Barker to Ned [i.e. Edward Spicer], May 12, 1957; Refers again to the joint publishing venture and comments on Spicer's paper. (Box 2, Folder 5, Item 11)
  - Letter from Wayland D. Hand to Barker, May 13, 1957; Discusses the use of photographs in Barker's article in Western Folklore (October issue). Article is on Yaqui Easter ceremonies. (Box 2, Folder 5, Item 12)
  - Letter from Barker to Wayland D. Hand, May 20, 1957; Promises a selection of photographs and the manuscript by the end of the month (cf. above letter). (Box 2, Folder 5, Item 13)
  - Letter from Barker to Esther Goldfrank, May 20, 1957; Requests information about a manuscript of Mexican dance drama originally collected by Elsie Clews Parsons. Barker had received the manuscript from Ralph Beals. (Box 2, Folder 5, Item 14)
  - Letter from Barker to Sheilagh and Richard Brooks, May 20, 1957; Contains suggestions for questions to ask their Informant (cf. the Brooks’s letter of April 27, 1957) in regard to their Los pastores play. Also mentions Elsie Clews Parson’s Mexican dance drama of the Mexican Revolution (cf. previous letter). (Box 2, Folder 5, Item 15)
  - Letter from Barker to Muriel Thayer Painter, June 15, 1957; Sends his manuscript of his paper on the Yaqui Easter ceremonies in Hermosillo, Mexico, and asks her comments. The letter also contains additional information on the Yaqui Easter ceremony. (Box 2, Folder 5, Item 16)
  - Letter from Wayland [i.e. Wayland D. Hand] to Barker, June 17, 1957; Friendly note. (Box 2, Folder 5, Item 17)
  - Letter from Barker to Eugenio Cabrero, June 20, 1957; Mentions a field trip to Spain to do research on the Spanish background of Southwestern religious folk dramas. Seeks support of the Del Amo Foundation. (Box 2, Folder 5, Item 18)
  - Letter from Barker to Russell H. Fitzgibbon, July 29, 1957; Concerns the financial support of his research on the Spanish background of Mexican folk dramas in the Southwest by the Del Amo Foundation (cf. previous letter). (Box 2, Folder 5, Item 19)
  - Letter from Barker to Sheilagh and Richard H. Brooks, September 14, 1957; Mentions the Brooks’s Los pastores play and some interesting parallels to other folk dramas of the time. Gives no specifics parallels, however. (Box 2, Folder 5, Item 20)
  - Letter from Barker to Russell H. Fitzgibbon, September 24, 1957; Outlines his research project in Spain for the Committee of Latin American Studies. Intends to study the Spanish background of the Southwestern folk dramas (cf. Barker’s letters of June 20 and July 29, 1957). (Box 2, Folder 5, Item 21)
  - Letter from Barker to Russell H. Fitzgibbon, October 17, 1957; Asks for an acknowledgment of the materials sent (cf. Barker’s letters of June 20 and July 29, 1957). (Box 2, Folder 5, Item 22)
  - Letter from Eugenio Cabrero to Barker, October 25, 1957; Del Amo Foundation declines to fund research in Spain. (Box 2, Folder 5, Item 23)
  - Letter from Richard and Sheilagh Brooks to Barker, October 26, 1957; Promises further talk with informant on the Los pastores manuscript. (Box 2, Folder 5, Item 24)
  - Letter from the Rev. Anthony Soto to Barker, February 11, 1958; Contains historical background of Pala Mission and gives also some general information of the Corpus Christi processions at the mission. (Box 2, Folder 5, Item 25)
  - Letter from Barker to the Rev. Anthony Soto, February 14, 1958; Acknowledges information and inquires about mission records, the changes in the Corpus Christi procession and changes in administration. (Box 2, Folder 5, Item 26)
  - Letter from the Rev. Anthony Soto to Barker, February 16, 1958; Provides the name of missionaries who worked at Pala. (Box 2, Folder 5, Item 27)
  - Letter from Barker to the Rev. Anthony Soto, February 19, 1958; Thanks Soto for his help and asks for information on other processions at San Luis Rey and Pala. Barker intends to make a study of the Pala Corpus Christi procession similar to the one he did on Yaqui Easter ceremonies at Hermosillo, Mexico. (Box 2, Folder 5, Item 28)
  - Letter from Richard H. Brooks to Barker, February 20, 1958; Asks Barker's advice on the publication of their Los pastores play. (Box 2, Folder 5, Item 29)
  - Letter from the Rev. Anthony Soto to Barker, February 24, 1958; Supplies additional information on processions at Pala and San Luis Rey and also gives a few sources. (Box 2, Folder 5, Item 30)
  - Letter from Barker to Richard H. Brooks, February 27, 1958; Promises to collaborate on the article to be published with the translation of the Brooks’ Los pastores play. (Box 2, Folder 5, Item 31)
  - Letter from Barker to the Rev. Anthony Soto, February 28, 1958; Acknowledges the information provided by Soto and asks for a brochure written by an Indian on early Indian life at San Luis Rey. (Box 2, Folder 5, Item 32)
  - Letter from Barker to the Rev. Anthony Soto, March 21, 1958; Mentions the receipt of Indian Life at Mission San Luis Rey and announces a visit to Pala during Holy Week. (Box 2, Folder 5, Item 33)
  - Letter from Barker to the Gift Shop, Old Mission San Luis Rey, California, March 21, 1958; Payment for Indian Life at Mission San Luis Rey, sent by the Rev. Anthony Soto. (Box 2, Folder 5, Item 34)
  - Letter from the Rev. Anthony Soto to Barker, March 24, 1958; Arranges a time for a visit with Barker during his intended visit (Holy Week). (Box 2, Folder 5, Item 35)
  - Postcard from Jean K. Adams (Pauma Valley Motor Lodge) to Barker, March 27, 1958; Confirms his reservation for Holy Week. (Box 2, Folder 5, Item 36)
  - Letter from Richard H. Brooks to Barker, April l, 1958; Confirms arrangement for collaboration on the Los pastores article. (Box 2, Folder 5, Item 37)
  - Letter from George Barker (Sr.) to Richard H. Brooks, May 7, 1958; Announces his son's death and returns the Los pastores manuscript. (Box 2, Folder 5, Item 38)
- Published and Unpublished Articles, Papers and Reviews, 1936-1958; Series III
  Text, illustrations, and captions of Barker's works. Printed publications appear first, followed by manuscript copies of informal essays and vignettes and then manuscripts of Barker's anthropological work, in loose chronological order. The Folk Drama subseries contains a handwritten transcript of a Christmas "shepherd's play" provided by Aristéo Flores of Chapalá, Mexico, and Barker's published bilingual edition of the text. Items are arranged by genre and thereunder roughly chronologically.
  - Publications (excluding The Shepherds' Play of the Prodigal Son. See box 2, folder 26), undated (Box 2, Folder 6-10)
  - Pilgrimage to Mexico [unpublished manuscript, typescript xerostatic copy], undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - "The Velorio;" illustrations intended to accompany Pilgrimage to Mexico, undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Essays, stories, vignettes: "Back-Country Notes" (1939), Hello Stranger, "Artist for the Million," "The Itinerant Buckeye Painter as Folk Artist: A Profile," and "Backwoods Rembrandt," all unpublished; and "Birthday Party for the Virgin" (New Mexico Folklore Record, 1950)., 1939; 1950 (Box 2, Folder 13-17)
  - "Vanishing Indian Cultures of Southern California" (Pacific Horizons, 1939). Typescript and copy of publication (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Papers, reviews, reports, 1943-1955, on language and linguistics: includes bibliography of sources relating to "Social Functions of Bilingualism"; "Investigating Human Behavior: First Notes for a Primer on General Semantics" (Los Angeles Society for General Semantics, 1939); "The Social Functions of Language" (Etc.: A Review of General Semantics, 1945); a review of Victor Grove's The Language Bar (Etc. A Review of General Semantics, 1952); and other papers and reviews., 1939; 1943-1955 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - "Growing Up in a Bilingual Community" (Kiva, 1951) (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Supplemental materials, prepared by Barker, for a "Ways of Justice" discussion program on international law, post 1950 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - "Notes on Some Conversations with Men of Mexican Descent in an Occupational Group", 1950-1951 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Papers on Yaqui and Pueblo adaptations of Spanish Catholic traditions, processions, and ceremony, 1956-1958 (Box 2, Folder 23-25)
  - “The Shepherds' Play of the Prodigal Son.” Folklore Studies 2 (1953). Publication (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Coloquio de pastores del hijo pródigo from Chapalá, Mexico. Handwritten transcription of folk drama, and related correspondence, 1949 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - The Prodigal Son suggested treatment, unpublished, undated (Box 2, Folder 28)
- Field and Research Notes, 1940-1958; Series IV
  Papers, minutes, field notes, M.A. and Ph.D. notes, and secondary research materials. Items are arranged by subject and thereunder chronologically.
  - Field notes and secondary research, ca. 1940-1944 (Box 2, Folder 29-34)
  - Field notes for M.A. thesis: "Functions of the Ancestral Language among American Immigrants and Their Descendants", 1943 (Box 2, Folder 35-36)
  - Field notes and secondary research, 1944-1947, primarily relating to field work in Tucson for his doctoral thesis: "Social Functions of Language in a Mexican-American Community" (Box 2, Folder 37-48)
  - Notes, Spanish and Mexican folk drama, 1948 (Box 3, Folder 1-2)
  - Field notes, including notes for Pilgrimage to Mexico, 1948-1949 (Box 3, Folder 3-4)
  - Vocabulary notes, Pachuco border language, undated (Box 3, Folder 5-17)
  - Interviews and notes, for "Notes on Some Conversations with Men of Mexican Descent in an Occupational Group.", 1950-1951 (Box 3, Folder 18-19)
  - Field and research notes, interviews, and follow-up studies, primarily for West Los Angeles Neighborhood Settlement Association work with gangs, 1949-1953 (Box 3, Folder 20-27)
  - Field and secondary-research notes, on Catholic ritual processions and ceremonies, Yaqui Indian Holy Week ceremonies, and New Mexican Pueblo Indian ceremonies, 1953-1957 (Box 3, Folder 28-33)
  - Field notes, Pala Indians; miscellaneous, 1957-1958 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Proposals, including proposals and other materials on semantics, bilingualism, school survey in Tucson, Pachuco language, and work with gangs in Los Angeles, 1939-1955 (Box 3, Folder 35-38)
  - Miscellaneous additions, working copies, 1940s, 1953 (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - Miscellaneous materials, including foundation lists, bibliographies, research and field notes and notebooks covering the entire scope of Barker's professional career, and material about his Pachuco language study and informants, undated (Box 3, Folder 40-44)
- Poems and Essays, 1927-1956; Series V
  Miscellaneous poetry and notes, and handwritten and typed copies of the essay "When I was a Child."
  - Published ephemera (clippings), primarily poetry, 1938-1950 (Box 3, Folder 45)
  - Essays and poems, 1927-1956 (Box 3, Folder 46)
  - When I Was a Child typescript, 1939 (Box 3, Folder 47)
  - When I Was a Child, holograph manuscript, and miscellaneous writing, May 25-31, 1939 (Box 3, Folder 48)
- Visual and Audio Materials, 1940s-1950s; Series VI
  There are 379 original color slides and 151 duplicates. Approximately 70 each of slides and duplicates are of Yaqui village scenes and Holy Week processions at Hermosillo, Sonora, Mexico. The rest are travel slides of various countries, largely unidentified. The slides are arranged as follows: unlabeled originals in metal mounts (220); cardboard-mounted duplicates (151), all marked "AV Services, U of A" (duplicates of the first 50 metal-mounted originals plus 1 unidentified slide from the same series, and of 100 of the cardboard-mounted originals); 159 originals in cardboard mounts.
  Photographic materials consist of 8” x 10” black and white enlargements of Yaqui Indian ceremonies; 12 black and white postcards of Easter ceremonies at Pascua village, Tucson, Arizona; of Yaqui leader Louis Hernandez; and of a cathedral in Guadalajara, Mexico; and several unidentified photos of various people and locations. There are 11 4” x 5” negatives of photos corresponding to the 8” x 10” enlargements of Yaqui ceremonies, one set marked “Hermosillo.”
  Audio materials consist of interviews and examples of the Pachuco language used by Tucson area gangs in the 1940s. The recordings were initially made on two 7” tape reels, one with a paper substrate. These original tapes were duplicated onto a 10" tape reel with background noise removed and an edited 7" working copy. These tape reels have themselves been copied onto working cassettes, and housed in the Southwest Folklore Center cassette tape collection, SWF 009, with the call numbers 85.2/C.1 and 85.2/R.1. Due to the sensitive and personal nature of the material Barker recorded, names of persons and other identifying information have been deleted from the working copy. The duplicate reels and the fragile, paper tape original are stored with the other original materials in the collection. (Note: the tapes open with classical piano music, followed by informal interactions and then the Pachuco interviews.)
  Items are arranged by type of material.
  - Suggested 20-minute presentation of the visual materials for “The Yaqui Easter Ceremony at Hermosillo;” undated rough index of slides (does not correspond to accessioned order or total number of originals, but contains identifying commentary) (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Slides, originals, in metal mounts, undated (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Slides, copies; followed by original slides in cardboard mounts, undated (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Photographs and postcards, undated (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Negatives, undated; The following boxes contain the original documents copied to make up the working collection described above. Material in the following boxes may only be used with the permission of the coordinator of the Southwest Folklore Center or the University of Arizona manuscripts librarian. The material is described in detail above. (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Background research notes, undated (Box 6, Folder 1-7)
  - Monographs, undated (Box 6, Folder 8-9)
  - Announcements, fliers, miscellaneous, undated (Box 6, Folder 10-11)
  - Correspondence, 1931, 1940-1958 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Published and unpublished articles, papers, and reviews, undated (Box 6, Folder 13-16)
  - Published and unpublished articles, papers, and reviews (continued), undated (Box 7, Folder 1-14)
  - Folk drama, undated (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - Field and research notes, undated (Box 7, Folder 16-20)
  - Field and research notes (continued), undated (Box 8, Folder 1-16)
  - Poems and personal writings (published ephemera), undated (Box 8, Folder 17)
  - Original tape reel (paper substrate; fragile), undated (Box 8, Folder 18)
  - Tape reel “master”, undated (Box 8, Folder 19)
  - Duplicated tape reels, undated; Duplicated tape reels of the materials in box 8, folders 18-19: a 10" restricted-use duplicate tape reel with background noise removed and a working 7" reel with names deleted; master cassette copies of the reels. (Box 9)